Keats, John, 1795-1821. John Keats portraits and artifacts (Keats Room): Guide.
John Keats portraits and artifacts,
ca. 1817-1970 and undated.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
Keats, John, 1795-1821.
15 items (2 linear ft.)
Portraits of English poet John Keats and objects owned by him.
Various accessions, various dates. See item description for full acquisition information.
The Keats Room and many of these objects can be viewed by guided tour Fridays at 2:00 p.m.
Examination of objects in the Houghton Reading Room requires advance notice, and the permission of the curator.
John Keats (1795-1821) was one of the principal poets of the English Romantic movement.
These objects, most of which are on permanent display in the Keats Room at Houghton Library, were acquired at various times and from various donors. Some items were owned by John Keats.
Organized into the following two series:
I. Portraits of John Keats
II. Objects owned by John Keats
Includes portraits of Keats: silhouette by Charles Armitage Brown (1819), bas-relief (sculpture) by Muriel Caswall (ca. 1945), portrait cameo in bone china (1970), three drawings by Joseph Severn (ca. 1818, 1830, 1860), and medallions by Sidney Waugh (1936); and mixed media by Ross Wilson. Also includes objects owned by Keats, including: gold bracelet (jewelry), gold seal with chain, tin box formerly housing a Book of Common Prayer (1817), locks of John Keats's hair (one in gold locket), and the prize medal awarded to Keats in 1810 while attending John Clarke's School in Enfield.
- I. Portraits of John Keats
  - Brown, Charles Armitage, 1786-1842, artist. John Keats: bust portrait silhouette, 1819., 1 item: paper; 13 x 10 cm. (visible image), 25 x 22 cm. (frame).
    Black paper cut-out, on cream-colored paper background.
    Left-side profile of face.
    With title under silhouette: John Keats / 1819.
    Probably cut by Charles Armitage Brown.
    In oval frame and glazed.
    *42M-486. Purchased with the Friends of the Harvard College Library fund from L. D. Peterkin, Applecroft, Andover, Massachusetts; received: 1943 January 15.
  - Caswall, Muriel, artist. John Keats: bust portrait bas-relief (sculpture); [Boston, ca. 1945]., 1 item: plaster; 13 x 8 x 2 cm.
    Inscribed title at bottom front: John Keats.
    Image taken from the life-mask and contemporary drawings of Keats. [description written at time of accessioning].
    Back has two metal hanger clips embedded in plaster.
    Right side of bas-relief is inscribed: © M. Caswall.
    *45Z-1. Gift of Miss Muriel Caswall, 86 Charles Street, Boston 14, Massachusetts; received: 1946 June 1.
  - John Keats: bust portrait cameo; [Barlaston, Staffordshire, England, 1970]., 1 item: white and Wedgwood blue bone china; 11 x 8 cm. (cameo); 21 x 17 cm. (frame).
    Right-side profile of face.
    Head is white china, background is blue china.
    Cameo is oval shaped, attached to rectangular black velvet background, then framed.
    *69Z-2. Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Arthur A. Houghton, Jr.; received: 1970 July.
  - Severn, Joseph, 1793-1879, artist. John Keats: bust portrait drawing, 1860., 1 item: watercolor, zinc white, pencil, on buff paper; 20 x 15 cm. (image), 34 x 29 cm. (frame)
    Bust portrait of Keats gazing to his left.
    Signed in lower right corner: Severn May 30 1860.
    Matted, glazed, and framed.
    No accession number. Donor unknown.
  - Severn, Joseph, 1793-1879. John Keats: bust portrait drawing, [ ca. 1830?]., 1 item in box: sepia (ink) on cream (color) paper; 18 x 14 cm. (image), 24 x 20 cm. (frame).
    Head portrait only, depicting left-side of his face.
    Paper watermarked 1829.
    Matted and glazed. In contemporary maple frame.
    Provenance:
    Label on back of frame: "This Sepia drawing of John Keats, the poet, by Severn, was presented to Dr. Samuel Steele of Abergavenny by Richard [sic] Trelawney, the friend of Byron, Shelley and Keats, when he was living at Cefn Ila, Usk, Mon., and was purchsed at the sale of the effects of Dr. D. Steele, son of Dr. Samuel Steele, at Abergavenny in 1902 by old James Barnes, a dealer of Newport, Mon. John Kyrle Fletcher purchased it from Barnes the day after the sale. The paper is watermarked 1829."
    Accession entry continues: Purchased by Arthur A. Houghton, Jr. from Ifan Kyrle Fletcher in 1965.
    Back of frame also with manuscript inscription: "Samuel Steele Esq MD."
    *65M-13. Gift of Arthur A. Houghton, Jr., 715 Fifth Avenue, New York 22, New York; received: 1965 July 13.
  - [Severn, Joseph, 1793-1879, attributed name]. John Keats: bust portrait drawing, [ca. 1818?], 1 item: pencil on paper; 9 x 7 cm. (image), 28 x 26 cm. (frame).
    Image is either by or after Joseph Severn. Similar image to *65M-13.
    No accession number. Gift of Arthur A. Houghton, Jr.
  - Waugh, Sidney, 1904-1963, artist. Homage to John Keats 1795-1821 medallion, 1936., 1 item: bronze; 10 cm. (diameter).
    One of five copies cast for the artist's personal use. No others were struck.
    Title taken from obverse text. Obverse includes image of Keats.
    With reverse text: The poetry of earth is never dead. Reverse includes image of a robed-Greek playing the lyre.
    Housed in case, with spine title: John Keats. Medal by Sidney Waugh.
    Inserted is an autograph manuscript letter from Waugh to Arthur A. Houghton, 1937 December 25, stating this medal was commissioned but never issued. With envelope.
    H37. Gift of Arthur A. Houghton, Jr., 1940. Gift to Arthur A. Houghton on December 25, 1937 by Sidney Waugh.
  - Waugh, Sidney, 1904-1963, artist. Homage to John Keats 1795-1821 medallion, 1936., 1 item: bronze; 10 cm. (diameter).
    Housed in case, with spine title: Waugh. Medallion of John Keats.
  - Wilson, Ross, 1957-. Keats as the crossed-out Christ, undated., 1 item: mixed media on paper; 21 x 14 cm. (image), 47 x 38 cm. (frame).
    A study from the life-mask of John Keats by Benjamin Robert Hyadon, 1816.
    Marked on back of frame: No. 15.
    *95M-50. Purchased with the Amy Lowell fund from Ross Wilson; received: 1996 March 20.
- II. Objects owned by John Keats
  - Box and lid, [ca. 1817]., 1 item in 2 pieces: tin; 4 x 11 x 7 cm.
    Rectangular tin box with separate lid.
    This item is the case for a volume received under the same accession number: Episcopal Church. The Book of Common Prayer, and administration of the sacraments; and other rites and ceremonies of the Church, according to the use of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States of America, together with the Psalter, or Psalms of David. Baltimore, Joseph N. Lewis [1817]. Houghton call number: Keats *EC8 K2262 Zy817p.
    *75-1447. Gift of Ella Keats Whiting,; Mrs. C. Randolph Myer,; John K. Whiting, Jr. '29, c/o Ella Keats Whiting, 17 Cottage Street, Wellesley, Massachusetts 02181; received: 1976 May.
  - Gold bracelet (jewelry), [before 1821]., 1 item: gold link metal chain with clasp; 19 cm. (length) x .5 cm (width).
    In wooden case, with satin cushion.
    Bracelet made from a portion of a gold chain originally given to Keats by an unidentified admirer. Keats gave it to his sister-in-law Georgiana, who thought it too long and shortened it by making one or more bracelets of the excess. Georgiana gave this bracelet to her daughter, Ella (Keats) Peay, who passed it along to her daughter, Mildred (Peay) Whiting, mother of the donors. [description written at time of accessioning].
    *75Z-3. Gift of Ella Keats Whiting,; Mrs. C. Randolph Myer, Jr., and John K. Whiting, Jr. '29, c/o Ella Keats Whiting 17 Cottage Street, Wellesley, Massachusetts 02181; received: 1976 May.
  - Gold seal and chain, [before 1821]., 1 item: gold metal, stone; 3 cm. (width of seal), 4 cm. (length of seal),19 cm. (total length seal and chain).
    Seal design is the letters "JK" with crown above and below letters (in semi-circular pattern); seal produces 2 x 2.5 cm. image.
    In style of chain with fob.
  - Lock of John Keats's hair, undated., 1 item: human hair.
    Hair is housed in a small, gold, oval locket, 3 x 2 cm. Locket is housed inside a leather case, 3 x 3 x 2 cm.
    Hair, locket, and small box are housed in case, 20 x 14 cm.
    Includes paper note with autograph manuscript in hand of Louis Arthur Holman, with text: "A couple of hairs from head of John Keats given to me by F[red]. H[olland]. Day, of Norwood, who has a 2nd bigger lock. L. A. Holman." Note folded and found in small leather case holding locket; removed to paper folder within larger case.
    No accession number. Probably gift of Arthur A. Houghton, Jr., 1940.
  - Lock of John Keats's hair, undated., 1 item: human hair.
    With a manuscript note: "Hair of Keats. Testified by Leigh Hunt."
    Part of H33. Gift of Arthur A. Houghton, Jr., 1941.
  - Rev Wm Thomas Academy Enfield prize medal, 1810., 1 item: silver; 5 cm. (diameter).
    Prize medal awarded to Keats while attending Clarke's School in Enfield
    With obverse text: Prize medal / Rev Wm Thomas / Academy Enfield / 1810 / Awarded to Master J. Keats.
    With reverse text: Stadium doctrina / arduum difficile / sit / nihilominus / fii gloriosus / erit. / Audivit / Clarkenem.
    With metal loop attached for hanging.
    Housed in case.